A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office Files of Louis Winnick FA601
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office Files of Louis Winnick
1950-2005
Rockefeller Archive Center
Winnick, Louis
Ford Foundation
FA601
12.6 Cubic Feet 32 boxes (27 letter document containers and 5 legal document containers)
Biographical/Historical note
Louis Winnick was born in Romania on April 1, 1921 and he immigrated to Brooklyn, New York when he was one year old. He later worked in the Brooklyn Navy Yard during World War II and graduated from Brooklyn College with a BA in History and Economics in 1946. He was awarded an MA (1947) and a PhD (1953) in Economics from Columbia University. He taught Economics at Brooklyn College (1948-1949), Columbia University (1947-1949) and Rutgers University (1949-1950) and joined the Institute for Urban Land Use and Housing Studies at Columbia University (1950-1955). Dr. Winnick's studies on housing economics, an important field of study during the post-war housing shortage, would guide his future career.
In November of 1957, Dr. Winnick was appointed Director of Research for the New York City Planning Commission. He then served as Executive Director of the Temporary State Commission on Economic Expansion (1959-1961) before becoming Chief of the Bureau of Planning and Research for the New York City Housing and Redevelopment Board (1961-1963).
Dr. Winnick joined the Ford Foundation in March of 1963 as a Program Associate for the Public Affairs Program. A year later, in February of 1964, he was appointed the Public Affairs Program's Associate Director (1964-1966). In 1967 he became Program Officer in Charge of the Urban and Metropolitan Development unit of the National Affairs Division and in June 1968 he was promoted to Deputy Vice President of the Division. He held this position through several Foundation-wide reorganizations for the remainder of his career. Dr. Winnick helped establish the Foundation's focus on urban renewal grants as a result of the urban turmoil of the 1960s. He is also credited with persuading Foundation President George McBundy to begin funding "program related investments" in the form of equity investments and low-interest loans to schools, hospitals, housing organizations and small businesses in low-income urban areas.
After his retirement in 1986, he returned as a consultant to work on several projects for the Foundation, including the Urban Crisis Study and a book, New People in Old Neighborhoods, published by the Russell Sage Foundation in 1990 about the Sunset Park neighborhood of New York City. Dr. Winnick died on July 29, 2006, at age 85.
The Foundation's work in the area of urban poverty began with the establishment of the Public Affairs Program in 1952. One of the goals of the new program was to work toward greater equality of opportunity for minority groups. In 1965, a National Affairs Division was created to focus on deep-rooted problems facing American society. Program areas under the National Affairs Division included Social Development, and Urban and Metropolitan Development. The United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) replaced National Affairs after a Foundation-wide reorganization in 1981. USIAP was broken up in another Foundation-wide reorganization in 1989.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 5 series.
File Plan note
Ford Foundation Resource Identifier: ACC2004/006
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. The RAC received an accession of Winnick's material from the Ford Foundation in 2019 as Accession 2019:075 (2.6 cu. ft.). This material has been added to the collection under Series III: Subject Files as Subseries 2: Subject Files Prior to Ford Foundation. At this time, another collection of Winnick material (previously RAC collection FA657: National Affairs, Urban and Metropolitan Development, Office Files of Louis Winnick) was combined with FA601 and the four folders that comprised this collection (.3 cu. ft.) were added to Series I and Series II. These folders can be found in Box 32.
Conditions Governing Access
Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Dr. Louis Winnick document his work as a Program Officer, Associate Director and Vice President of the Foundation's National Affairs Division. The files also include some of his pre-Foundation files relating to his work on housing economics and urban renewal, and research for his post-retirement work on a Ford Foundation-funded consultancy grant. The bulk of these files date from 1960-1973, roughly the first half of Dr. Winnick's career with the Ford Foundation.
Dr. Winnick's leadership helped direct the Foundation towards a focus on urban renewal grants in the 1960s, and this is documented in his office files. The topic of urban development, and in particular the creation of affordable middle class housing in urban areas, appears to have been of particular interest to Dr. Winnick. Even before he joined the Foundation, Dr. Winnick attended conferences on the topic (see, e.g., Rental Housing Conference, 4/25-4/26/1957) and he continued to attend conferences as a representative of the Foundation (refer to the Conferences series).
Dr. Winnick's speeches and writing, which span from 1956-1967, reveal his long interest in the subjects of rental housing and urban renewal as well as the impact private foundations could have on urban development. Similarly, Dr. Winnick's post-retirement involvement on a Ford-funded Urban Crisis Study shows the topic continued to be of interest to him throughout his life. His Study work file, along with drafts and notes related to his book on the Sunset Park neighborhood, are available in the collection.
The Office Files of Dr. Louis Winnick span from 1956 to 1958 and consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, grantee and proposal evaluations, conference and meeting materials, and background information documenting his work on the field of urban renewal and urban development. The bulk of the files consist of subject files on a variety of topics including grantees, Foundation-related task forces, program areas or meetings, and areas or organizations of personal interest. His speeches and writings and the working file from his post-retirement Ford-funded grant are also available.
Note from original processors at the Ford Foundation: Ford Foundation Resource Identifier: ACC95/3 – Records, 1953-1976, 1967-1976 (bulk). This collection of office files was created by the Division of National Affairs, its subsidiary programs and its program and consultant staff. There is some material from National Affairs' predecessor program, Public Affairs. These files were maintained by the following Foundation staff members: Christopher Edley, Sanford M. Jaffe, William Pincus, Esther Schachter, Robert Goldmann, George Esser, Mitchell Sviridoff, David B. Carlson, John R. Coleman, Thomas E. Cooney, Ronald T. Gault, Eamon Kelly, Robert Schrank, William Pendleton and Louis Winnick. Also included are the chronological correspondence files of the Government and Law and the Resources and Environment programs.
- Conferences, 1957-1969; I
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Dr. Winnick's conference files document his continued interest and activity in the field of housing and urban studies both before and after he joined the Foundation. The files contain meeting books with agenda or programs, Dr. Winnick's handwritten notes, reports or transcripts from the conferences, and pre-conference background information.
  - Rental Housing Conference -- Agenda, Background Material incl. Summary of Winnick Address, 1957 April 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bankers Trust Company -- Real Estate Mortgage Financing Discussion, 1957 December 31-1959 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Steps Toward Economic Expansion in New York State: Report of the Temporary State Commission on Economic Expansion", 1960 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 18th Annual Conference for Senior Executives in Mortgage Banking, New York University -- Program, Speech, Background, 1963 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Space, Science and Urban Life Conference, Dunsmuir House, Oakland, CA -- Notes, Meeting Material, Speech, 1963 March 28-30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Savings and Loan League -- Conference on Saving and Financing, Chicago, IL -- Conference Book, 1963 May 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Engineering Foundation -- Urban Transportation Research Conference, Andover, NH -- Notes, Background, Speech, 1963 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation -- Gray Areas Research Directors Conference -- Proposed Agenda, Notes, Background, 1963 September 20-23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation -- Public Affairs Staff Conference, Ridgefield, CT -- Memoranda Re: Municipal Government, Electronic Data Processing, Scholarship Program, Notes, Assignments Resulting from Meeting, 1963 October 2-4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wealth Inventory Planning Study -- Working Group on Finance, Insurance, and Real Estate -- Meeting Summary, Working Group Report, Background, 1963 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ford Foundation -- Urban Extension Conference, New York, NY -- Agenda, Notes, 1963 October 27-29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Institute of Planners Annual Conference -- "Problems of Poverty and Race Confront the Planner" Panel, Milwaukee, WI -- Proceedings, Background, Notes, 1963 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Architectural Forum -- Middle Income Housing Discussion -- Article Based on Transcript, 1963 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Urban Affairs Conference, Long Island University -- Speech on Ford Foundation Role in Urban Affairs, 1964 March 7 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - TIME, Inc. -- Urban Renewal Symposium -- Transcript, Agenda, Background, 1964 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Trip to Europe (Tel Aviv, Athens, Rome, Dubrovnik, Belgrade, Zagreb, Amsterdam, London) -- Re: Urban Planning, 1964 June 23-July 25 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ditchley Foundation -- Seminar on Greater Metropolitan Planning, Ditchley Park, England -- Paper on Urban Land Value, Background, 1964 July 17-24 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - National Industrial Conference Board -- Business in 1965 Workshop, New York, NY -- Re: Non-Residential Construction, 1964 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation -- Public Affairs Staff Conference, Ridgefield, CT -- Agenda for Review of Public Affairs Programs, 1964 October 7-9 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - New York City Planning Commission -- Future by Design Conference -- Background on NYC Comprehensive Plan, 1964 October 14-16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Affairs Nonprofit Corporations (MANC) Organizations Meeting, Bloomfield Hills, MI -- Re: Role of Nonprofits in Solving Regional Problems, 1965 February 11-15 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - DAEDALUS -- Planning Committee on Shaping the American Future, Harvard University -- Report, Correspondence Re: Planning Meeting, 1965 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Seminars on Urban Renewal in the City of New York, New School for Social Research -- Participants List, Correspondence Re: Planning, 1965 March-April (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ford Foundation -- Public Affairs Staff Conference, Ridgefield, CT -- Planning Questions, Notes on Domestic Programs, 1965 April 7-8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Council on Foundations --16th Annual Conference, Pittsburgh, PA -- Notes on Meeting, Program, Background, 1965 May 19-21 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research -- Conference on Investment Behavior -- Paper and Comments on Intra-Metropolitan Population Distribution (1 of 2), 1965 June 10-12 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research -- Conference on Investment Behavior -- Paper and Comments on Intra-Metropolitan Population Distribution (2 of 2), 1965 June 10-12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ford Foundation -- Public Service Training Meeting -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: State-Local Training Program, Background (1 of 2), 1965 June 15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation -- Public Service Training Meeting -- Conference Meeting Transcript (2 of 2), 1965 June 15 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Regional Plan Association Annual Conference, New York, NY -- Program, Agenda, Background, 1965 November 10 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Friends Service Committee -- Conference on Self-Help Housing, Warrenton, VA -- Handwritten Notes, Background, 1965 December 6-9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Symposium on "The Middle North" at Wingspread, Racine, WI -- Background Material, 1966 April 22-24 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Inter-University Seminar on Urban Extension, Rutgers -- Reports on University Use of Ford Foundation Funds, 1966 May 2-3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Council on Foundations -- 17th Annual Conference, Denver, CO -- "Evaluation: Applications and Grantee Performance" (report), 1966 May 11-13 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Office of Economic Opportunity -- Housing and Urban Development Conference on Housing for the Poor -- Correspondence, Background, 1966 May 23-24 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Brookings Institute Conference on Negative Income Taxation -- Discussion Summary, 1966 June 8-9 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Taxation, Resources and Economic Development -- Conference on Property Tax and Economic Development, University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee -- Program, Background, 1966 June 13-15 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Urban Design Conference, Harvard University -- Re: Post-Professional Education, 1966 June 17 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Visit to Alaska -- Itinerary, Background, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Trip to Europe (Ljubljana, Slovenia; Brussells, Belgium) -- Trip Notes, Correspondence, Background, 1966 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Urban America Conference on "Our People and Their Cities," Washington, DC -- Program, Background, 1966 September 11-13 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Plan of Action for Tomorrow's Housing (PATH) Committee Meeting, Cleveland, OH -- Report, Comments, 1966 September 22 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Seminar on Land Taxation, University of Hartford, CT, 1966 October 18-21 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Twin City Metropolitan Seminar, Session on Governmental Structure, St. Thomas College, St. Paul, MN -- Agenda, Background, 1966 November 10 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Regional Plan Association -- Committee on the Second Regional Plan Meeting, New York, NY -- Agenda, Background Reading, 1966 November 29 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - United Nations Meeting on Trends in Housing Design Project, New York, NY -- Correspondence, Project Description, 1966 December 16 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Academy of Political Science Conference on Modernizing State Government: The New York Constitutional Convention of 1967, New York, NY -- Correspondence, Background, 1967 January 11 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Regional Plan Association -- Committee on the Second Regional Plan, Carnegie Endowment International Center, NY -- Program, Attendee List, 1967 March 22 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Urban Public Economics Meeting, New York University -- Re: Urban Housing and Renewal, 1967 April 7-8 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - House & Home -- Round Table on Middle and Low Income Housing, New York Hilton -- Transcript, Statement, 1967 May 23-24 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Social Science Research Council -- Conference on Federal-State-Local Relations, Brookings Institute, Washington, DC, 1967 June 21 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - National Association of Home Builders -- National Housing Goals Planning Conference, Washington, DC -- Correspondence, Discussion Materials, 1967 November 21 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Seminar on "Urban Development: What Role for Private Participation," The New School Center for New York City Affairs, 1967 November 30 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Panel Discussion on Housing Costs, The New School -- Correspondence, including with Sen. Paul H. Douglas, Background, 1968 February 20 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - PENJERDEL Regional Conference Housing Panel, Swarthmore College -- Correspondence, Program, Background, 1968 June 12 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - State of New Jersey Department of Community Affairs -- Meeting on Development of Hackensack Meadowlands -- Correspondence, Background, 1968 September 27-30 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company -- Savings and Loan Luncheon -- Handwritten Notes, Invitation List, Background, 1968 October 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ditchley Foundation Anglo-American Conference on New Towns, Ditchley Park, England -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Conference Reports, Background, 1968 November 15-18 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Inter-University Committee on Urban Economics (CUE) Research Conference Re: Urban Growth, Ghettos, Public Policy -- Background Papers (1 of 2), 1969 September 11-12 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Inter-University Committee on Urban Economics (CUE) Research Conference Re: Urban Problems -- Memoranda, Participants, Program, Background Papers (2 of 2), 1969 September 11-12 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Blue Collar Alienation, 1970 January 22 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, 1970 May 28 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - City Building Conference -- Columbia, MD, 1970 November 4-6 (Box 32, Folder 9)
- Correspondence and Memoranda, 1964-2005; II
  This series holds Dr. Winnick's chronological files maintained throughout his tenure at the Ford Foundation. The correspondence and memoranda for the years 1967 and 1987 to 1994 are not available. The documents focus on the National Affairs Program, grantees and proposals. The majority of the files hold correspondence with then-current, former or potential grant recipients. Some files also contain memoranda about grant modifications, reports on grantees by program officers, reviews of the National Affairs Program (12/29/1980), accounts of telephone conversations and meetings, and specific grant proposals, such as a memorandum dated May 10, 1974, from Dr. Winnick to President Bundy reflecting on future options for the Fund for the City of New York and the Fund for Michigan.
  Other correspondence pertains to the Urban and Metropolitan Development program (1971 to 1982), which Dr. Winnick continued to direct as Program Officer in Charge. He also corresponded with colleagues and commented on academic publications (1964-2005).
  - 1964 Chron File (1 of 2), 1964 May-August (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1964 Chron File (2 of 2), 1964 September-December (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1965 Chron File (1 of 2), 1965 January-May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1965 Chron File (2 of 2), 1965 June-December (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1966 Chron File (1 of 2), 1966 January-June (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1966 Chron File (2 of 2), 1966 July-December (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1968 Chron File (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1969 Chron File (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1970 Chron File (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - 1971 Chron File (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1972 Chron File (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1973 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1974 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1975 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1976 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1977 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1978 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 1979 Chron File (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 1980 Chron File (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1981 Chron File (1 of 2), 1981 January-March (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1981 Chron File (2 of 2), 1981 April-December (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1982 Chron File (1 of 2), 1982 January-June (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1982 Chron File (2 of 2), 1982 July-December (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1983 Chron File (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1984 Chron File (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1985 Chron File (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1986 Chron File, 1986 January-April (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Includes Winnick resume
  - 1995-2005 Chron File (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Chron File, Marcia Bikales -- DAP Grant Proposals, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1971 UMD Chron File (1 of 2), 1971 January-June (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1971 UMD Chron File (2 of 2), 1971 July-December (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1972 UMD Chron File (1 of 2), 1972 January-June (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1972 UMD Chron File (2 of 2), 1972 July-December (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1973 UMD Chron File (1 of 2), 1973 January-May (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1973 UMD Chron File (2 of 2), 1973 June-December (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1974 UMD Chron File (1 of 2), 1974 January-May (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1974 UMD Chron File (2 of 2), 1974 June-December (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1975 UMD Chron file (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1976 UMD Chron File (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1980 UMD Chron File (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1950-1974; III
  Dr. Winnick created subject files for grantees and grant projects, Foundation policy, program areas and task forces. There are also files pertaining to his interests and work, external organizations in which he served, and for individuals within and without the Foundation with whom he had regular contact. Some of the files pre-date his employment at the Ford Foundation.
  - Ford Foundation Subject Files, 1955-1974; 1
    While some subject files predate Winnick's employment with the Ford Foundation, the majority of the files in this series were created during his tenure at the Foundation.
    - American Council To Improve Our Neighborhoods (ACTION) -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Report on ACTION Housing Study, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - American Council To Improve Our Neighborhoods (ACTION) -- Research Council Committee Correspondence Re: Rental Housing, etc., 1957-1959 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Building Codes -- Correspondence with American Institute of Architects, Newsletters, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Building Codes Project, Gurney Breckenfeld -- Interview Notes (1 of 2), 1965 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Building Codes Project, Gurney Breckenfeld -- Interview Notes (2 of 2), 1965 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Building Codes Project, Gurney Breckenfeld -- Correspondence, Draft Report to Ford, Addendums, 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Center for Community Development Policy -- Proposal, Correspondence, Meeting Memoranda, List of Ford Foundation Rural Economic Development Grants, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Citizen Advice Bureaus/Ombudsman -- Memoranda, Clippings, Report on Possible American Uses, 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Citizens' Housing and Planning Council (CHPC) -- Board of Directors Meetings Re: Welfare Island Redevelopment, Battery Park City, Lincoln Center, etc. -- Agenda, Minutes (1 of 2), 1969 January-April (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Citizens' Housing and Planning Council (CHPC) -- Board of Directors Meetings Re: Welfare Island Redevelopment, United Nations Development Council, etc. -- Agenda, Minutes (2 of 2), 1969 May-December (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Citizens' Housing and Planning Council (CHPC) -- Board of Directors Meetings Re: NYC Housing Law, etc. -- Agenda, Memoranda, 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Commerce and Industry Association of New York -- Statement on High Value Public Housing, Workshop on Government Financial Aids to Construction, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Commission on Race and Housing -- Correspondence Re: Winnick Interest in Proposed Research Project on Mortgage Credit Availability to Minorities, 1955 December 1-1956 January 18 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Committee for Economic Development -- Background for Luncheon Meeting on NYC Metropolitan Growth, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Cooperative Assistance Fund -- Ford Foundation PRI, Board of Trustees Meeting Notes and Reports (1 of 3), 1971 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Cooperative Assistance Fund -- Ford Foundation PRI, Board of Trustees, etc. (2 of 3), 1972 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Cooperative Assistance Fund -- Ford Foundation PRI, Board of Trustees, etc. (3 of 3), 1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Drug Abuse Council -- Grant Action Recommendation for Drug Abuse Research Project and Memoranda, 1970-1973 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Downtown Economists Luncheon Group -- Meeting Agenda, Club Reports, 1961-1963 (Box 13, Folder 3)